A Guide to the Richard Beale Davis Papers
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Richard Beale Davis Papers 1584-ca. 1700, 1934-1978
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
462-a
This collection consists of ca. 1,000 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Richard Beale Davis papers were bequeathed to the University of Virginia on September 23, 1981.
Biographical/Historical Information
Richard Beale Davis was born in Accomac, Virginia and received his Ph.D. from the University of Virginia in 1936. He subsequently taught at Mary Washington College (1936-1940) and the University of South Carolina (1940-1962) before becoming professor in English at the University of Tennessee (1962-1981). His chief fields of study included intellectual life in the colonial south, colonial and early American literature, and Edgar Allan Poe. Among Davis' secondary interests was George Sandys (1578-1644), about whom he published numerous articles, monographs, and the standard Sandys biography.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists chiefly of the research files and correspondence of Richard Beale Davis (1907-1981). Besides Davis' letters and research notes, this collection also includes photostatic copies of sixteenth and seventeenth-century manuscripts and books, newsclippings (chiefly book notices and reviews of Davis' George Sandys, Poet-Adventurer), letters of agreement and investment statements from Davis' publishers, typed and autograph manuscripts of articles about George Sandys, photographs and printed matter.
Most of the documents in this collection pertain to Davis' research and published works about George Sandys, who has been described as being the first man in America to devote himself seriously to literature and scholarship. Sandys had been a shareholder in the Virginia Company since 1607 and sailed to America in 1621 as the company's newly-elected treasurer. He was of primary importance following the Jamestown Massacre of 1622, and in 1624 he became a member of Virginia's colonial council. Sandys' interest in Virginia continued after his return to England (post 1628), and he represented the colony's interests when the Virginia assembly petitioned for restoration of charter rights in 1640. Sandys' best known literary work, first published in 1621 and composed in part during his Atlantic crossing, was an English translation of Ovid's Metamorphosis. Among his other works are A Paraphrase Upon the Psalmes(sic) of David (and Hyms dispersed throughout the Old and New Testaments)(1636); A Paraphrase Upon the Divine Poems(1638); Christ's Passion(translated from Grotius) (1640); A Paraphrase Upon the Song of Solomon(1641, 1642).
Most of the letters in this collection comprise reference inquiries and professional correspondence between Davis and his colleagues. Among the correspondents are J. Lindsay Almond, Francis L. Berkeley, Jr., Fredson T. Bowers, Lester J. Cappon, Harry M. Meacham, John B. Morrell (Lord Mayor of York) and John Cook Wyllie. Letters to and from various research libraries, as well as correspondence with Davis' publishers (Columbia University Press and the Bodley Head) and with the editors of various periodicals, are also present. These letters, which discuss bibliographical, historical and literary aspects of George Sandys' career, also document the progress of Davis' research. A separate group of correspondence pertains to the Sandys family and includes genealogical information and personal letters between Davis and some of George Sandys' descendents.
The printed matter in this collection consists mainly of reprint articles about George Sandys' works, but also includes book reviews and notices of Davis' biography of him. Photographs and illustrations, including those used in George Sandys, Poet Adventurer, depict Jamestown and provide likenesses of George Sandys and others in the Sandys family.
Arrangement
These papers are grouped topically as Davis had them arranged. Folder headings, with slight modifications, have been maintained. Letters within each heading are arranged chronologically, and photostatic copies and printed matter have been placed following the correspondence folders.
Contents List
- Correspondence and related papers re research on George Sandys 1934, 1938-1942, 1946-1950, [1953-1955], 1978, n.d. (Box 1)
  417 items (3 folders)
- Correspondence and related papers re George Sandys' A Paraphrase Upon the Song of Solomon1937, 1941-1942, 1955-1956, 1962, n.d. (Box 1)
  39 items
- Correspondence and related papers re "America in George Sandys' 'Ovid' [Metamorphosis]" 1938-1941, 1947-1950, n.d. (Box 1)
  41 items
- Correspondence and newspaper clippings re Sandys' family 1939, [1947-1964], 1973, n.d. (Box 1)
  87 items
- Correspondence re George Sandys' A Paraphrase Upon the Divine Poems1947, 1949 (Box 1)
  3 items
- Correspondence and related papers re George Sandys' Relation...1947-1948, 1972-1973, n.d. (Box 2)
  8 items
- Re Sandys' Christ's Passion1949, n.d. (Box 2)
  2 items
- Correspondence and related papers re publication of George Sandys... by Columbia University Press and Bodley Head [1949-1956], 1977 (Box 2)
  156 items
- Correspondence and related papers re Sandys' 1623 edition of Ovid's Metamorphosis, including TMs of "In re George Sandys' Ovid" w/corrections 1954-1955, n.d. (Box 2)
  14 items
- Correspondence and related papers re "Volumes from the George Sandys Library Now in America" 1954-1957, n.d. (Box 2)
  49 items
- Correspondence, newsclippings and printed notices re George Sandys... 1955-1956 (Box 2)
  28 items
- Correspondence re John Tradescant (fl. 1640) 1962 (Box 2)
- Correspondence re George Sandys' 1632 edition of Ovid's Metamorphosis1962-1963, 1968 (Box 2)
  20 items
- Correspondence re "Sandys, George," Encyclopaedia Britannica(1966) w/enclosed TMs 1963 (Box 2)
  5 items
- Correspondence re George Sandys' Library 1967 (Box 2)
- Photostatic copy of George Sandys' A Paraphrase Upon the Divine Poem1638 (Box 2)
  1 item
- Photostats, transcriptions and abstracts of 16th and 17th century documents re George Sandys 1584-ca. 1700 (Box 2)
  23 items
- Photographs, etchings and seal(wax) re Sandys family and Jamestown 1823, 1907, 1937, n.d. (Box 2)
  15 items
- Reviews and notices clipped from American publications re George Sandys[1955-1956], 1960, n.d. (Box 2)
  43 items
- Public Records Office C.8/15/92/4-5 1603, Photostatic Copy
- Public Records Office E.112/215/831/2 1635, Photostatic Copy
- Public Records Office C.24/629/32 1638, Photostatic Copy
- Public Records Office E.125/20/136d-137d n.d., Photostatic Copy
- Textual comparisons of various editions of Sandys' A Paraphrase Upon the Song of Solomonn.d., TMs and AMs
- Miscellaneous printed material re George Sandys et. al. 1941-1947, n.d.
  17 items
- Reprints of articles by R. B. Davis re George Sandys 1948-1966
  7 items